Why the heck should we do this? 12 years ago, I gave a TED talk on 10 ways the world could end suddenly. We are incredibly vulnerable to the whims of our own galaxy. A single, large asteroid could take us out forever. To survive we have to reach beyond the home planet. Think what a tragedy it would be if all that humans have accomplished were suddenly obliterated. And there's another reason we should go: exploration is in our DNA. Two million years ago humans evolved in Africa and then slowly but surely spread out across the entire planet by reaching into the wilderness that was beyond their horizons. This stuff is inside us. And they prospered doing that. Some of the greatest advances in civilization and technology came because we explored. Yes, we could do a lot of good with the money it will take to establish a thriving colony on Mars. And yes we should all be taking far better care of our own home planet. And yes, I worry we could screw up Mars the way we've screwed up Earth. But think for a moment, what we had when John F. Kennedy told us we would put a human on the moon. He excited an entire generation to dream. Think how inspired we will be to see a landing on Mars. Perhaps then we will look back at Earth and see that that is one people instead of many and perhaps then we will look back at Earth, as we struggle to survive on Mars, and realize how precious the home planet is. So let me tell you about the extraordinary adventure we're about to undertake. But first, a few fascinating facts about where we're going. This picture actually represents the true size of Mars compared to Earth. Mars is not our sister planet. It's far less than half the size of the Earth, and yet despite the fact that it's smaller, the surface area of Mars that you can stand on is equivalent to the surface area of the Earth that you can stand on, because the Earth is mostly covered by water.
¿Por qué diablos deberíamos hacerlo? Hace 12 años, di una charla TED nombrando 10 causas posibles del fin del mundo. Somos muy vulnerables a los caprichos de nuestra propia galaxia. Un único e inmenso asteroide podría eliminarnos para siempre. Para sobrevivir tenemos que conquistar otros planetas. Piensen qué trágico sería si todos los logros de la humanidad desaparecieran de repente. Y hay otra razón para esta exploración: es parte de nuestro ADN. Hace dos millones de años, los humanos evolucionaron en África para luego, poco a poco extenderse por todo el planeta y adentrarse en tierras salvajes más allá de sus hogares. Lo llevamos dentro. Y prosperaron haciendo eso. Algunos de los mayores avances de la civilización y la tecnología surgieron porque exploramos. Es cierto que podríamos hacer mucho bien con el dinero que se necesita para establecer una próspera colonia en Marte. Y claramente debemos hacer mucho más para el cuidar a nuestra madre Tierra. Y sí, me preocupa que pudiéramos estropear Marte de la misma manera que hicimos con la Tierra. Pero piensen por un momento lo que teníamos cuando John F. Kennedy dijo que íbamos a llevar al hombre a la luna: animó a toda una generación a soñar. Piensen que emocionados estaríamos por ver un amartizaje. Tal vez entonces, al mirar de vuelta a la Tierra entenderíamos que está hecha por un pueblo en lugar de por muchos; y tal vez entonces, al mirarla, mientras lucháramos por sobrevivir en Marte, nos daríamos cuenta de lo preciosa que es nuestro madre Tierra. Permítanme hablarles de la extraordinaria aventura que estamos a punto de emprender, pero primero, compartiré algunos datos fascinantes acerca de dónde vamos. En esta imagen se aprecia el tamaño real de Marte comparado con la Tierra. Marte no es nuestro planeta hermano. Tiene mucho menos de la mitad del tamaño de la Tierra, y sin embargo, a pesar de ser más pequeño, la superficie habitable marciana es equivalente a la superficie habitable terrestre ya que la Tierra está cubierta por agua.
The atmosphere on Mars is really thin -- 100 times thinner than on Earth -- and it's not breathable, it's 96 percent carbon dioxide. It's really cold there. The average temperature is minus 81 degrees, although there is quite a range of temperature. A day on Mars is about as long as a day on Earth, plus about 39 minutes. Seasons and years on Mars are twice as long as they are on Earth.
La atmósfera marciana es muy tenue -- 100 veces más delgada que la terrestre -- y no es respirable, tiene un 96 % de dióxido de carbono. Hace mucho frío allí. La temperatura media es de - 62 °C aunque varía ampliamente. Un día marciano es casi tan largo como un día en la Tierra, más unos 39 minutos. Las estaciones y los años en Marte son dos veces más largos.
And for anybody who wants to strap on some wings and go flying one day, Mars has a lot less gravity than on Earth, and it's the kind of place where you can jump over your car instead of walk around it. Now, as you can see, Mars isn't exactly Earth-like, but it's by far the most livable other place in our entire solar system. Here's the problem. Mars is a long way away, a thousand times farther away from us than our own moon. The Moon is 250,000 miles away and it took Apollo astronauts three days to get there. Mars is 250 million miles away and it will take us eight months to get there -- 240 days. And that's only if we launch on a very specific day, at a very specific time, once every two years, when Mars and the Earth are aligned just so, so the distance that the rocket would have to travel will be the shortest. 240 days is a long time to spend trapped with your colleagues in a tin can. And meanwhile, our track record of getting to Mars is lousy. We and the Russians, the Europeans, the Japanese, the Chinese and the Indians, have actually sent 44 rockets there, and the vast majority of them have either missed or crashed. Only about a third of the missions to Mars have been successful. And we don't at the moment have a rocket big enough to get there anyway. We once had that rocket, the Saturn V. A couple of Saturn Vs would have gotten us there. It was the most magnificent machine ever built by humans, and it was the rocket that took us to the Moon. But the last Saturn V was used in 1973 to launch the Skylab space station, and we decided to do something called the shuttle instead of continuing on to Mars after we landed on the Moon. The biggest rocket we have now is only half big enough to get us anything to Mars. So getting to Mars is not going to be easy and that brings up a really interesting question ... how soon will the first humans actually land here? Now, some pundits think if we got there by 2050, that'd be a pretty good achievement. These days, NASA seems to be saying that it can get humans to Mars by 2040. Maybe they can. I believe that they can get human beings into Mars orbit by 2035. But frankly,
Y para cualquiera que quiera ponerse alas y volar un día, dada la menos gravedad que en la Tierra, Marte se vuelve el tipo de lugar
I don't think they're going to bother in 2035 to send a rocket to Mars, because we will already be there. We're going to land on Mars in 2027. And the reason is this man is determined to make that happen. His name is Elon Musk, he's the CEO of Tesla Motors and SpaceX. Now, he actually told me that we would land on Mars by 2025,
no creo que querrán enviar un cohete a Marte en 2035 porque ya estaremos allí. Vamos a aterrizar en Marte en 2027. Y la razón es que este hombre está decidido a hacerlo realidad. Se llama Elon Musk y es el CEO de Tesla Motors y SpaceX. De hecho me confirmó el aterrizaje en 2025,
but Elon Musk is more optimistic than I am -- and that's going a ways -- so I'm giving him a couple of years of slack. Still ... you've got to ask yourself, can this guy really do this by 2025 or 2027? Well, let's put a decade with Elon Musk into a little perspective. Where was this 10 years ago? That's the Tesla electric automobile. In 2005, a lot of people in the automobile industry were saying, we would not have a decent electric car for 50 years. And where was that? That is SpaceX's Falcon 9 rocket, lifting six tons of supplies to the International Space Station. 10 years ago, SpaceX had not launched anything, or fired a rocket to anywhere. So I think it's a pretty good bet that the person who is revolutionizing the automobile industry in less than 10 years and the person who created an entire rocket company in less than 10 years will get us to Mars by 2027. Now, you need to know this: governments and robots no longer control this game. Private companies are leaping into space and they will be happy to take you to Mars. And that raises a really big question. Can we actually live there? Now, NASA may not be able to get us there until 2040, or we may get there a long time before NASA,
pero, Elon Musk es más optimista que yo, y eso es decir mucho, así que le doy un margen de un par de años. No obstante, tienen que preguntarse, ¿puede hacerlo realidad para el año 2025 o 2027? Veamos qué significa una década para Elon Musk. ¿Dónde estaba hace 10 años? Ese es el auto eléctrico Tesla. En 2005, muchos en la industria automovilística decían que no íbamos a tener un auto eléctrico decente en los siguientes 50 años. ¿Y dónde ocurrió eso? Este es el cohete Falcon 9 de SpaceX, llevando seis toneladas de suministros a la Estación Espacial Internacional. Hace 10 años, SpaceX no lanzó nada, no mandó un cohete a ningún lugar. Por lo tanto creo que merece apostar por la persona que revolucionó la industria del automóvil en menos de 10 años y la persona que creó toda una empresa aeroespacial en menos de 10 años para que nos lleve a Marte antes de 2027. Ahora, hay algo que deben saber: los gobiernos y los robots ya no controlan este negocio. las empresas privadas conquistan el espacio y estarán encantadas de llevarles a Marte. Y esto plantea otra gran pregunta: ¿Podemos realmente vivir allí? La NASA a lo mejor no podrá llegar allí hasta el año 2040, o a lo mejor nosotros podemos llegar allí mucho antes que la NASA,
but NASA has taken a huge responsibility in figuring out how we can live on Mars. Let's look at the problem this way. Here's what you need to live on Earth: food, water, shelter and clothing. And here's what you need to live on Mars: all of the above, plus oxygen. So let's look at the most important thing on this list first. Water is the basis of all life as we know it, and it's far too heavy for us to carry water from the Earth to Mars to live, so we have to find water if our life is going to succeed on Mars. And if you look at Mars, it looks really dry, it looks like the entire planet is a desert. But it turns out that it's not. The soil alone on Mars contains up to 60 percent water. And a number of orbiters that we still have flying around Mars have shown us -- and by the way, that's a real photograph --
pero la NASA tiene un enorme mérito porque averigua cómo podemos vivir allí. Veamos el problema de esta manera. Esto es lo que necesita para vivir en la Tierra: alimento, agua, refugio y ropa. Y esto es lo que necesita para vivir en Marte: todo lo anterior, más oxígeno. Así que primero, vamos a ver la cosa más importante de la lista. El agua está en la base de la vida tal como la conocemos y es demasiado pesada para llevarla de la Tierra a Marte para sobrevivir, así que tenemos que encontrar agua si queremos que la vida en Marte sea un éxito. Y si nos fijamos en Marte, se ve muy seco, parece que todo el planeta es un desierto. Pero resulta que no lo es. El suelo marciano, por sí solo, contiene hasta un 60 % de agua. y varios satélites que mantenemos todavía en la órbita de Marte nos han demostrado -- por cierto, esta es una fotografía real --
that lots of craters on Mars have a sheet of water ice in them. It's not a bad place to start a colony. Now, here's a view of a little dig the Phoenix Lander did in 2008, showing that just below the surface of the soil is ice -- that white stuff is ice. In the second picture, which is four days later than the first picture, you can see that some of it is evaporating. Orbiters also tell us that there are huge amounts of underground water on Mars as well as glaciers. In fact, if only the water ice at the poles on Mars melted, most of the planet would be under 30 feet of water. So there's plenty of water there, but most of it's ice, most of it's underground, it takes a lot of energy to get it and a lot of human labor. This is a device cooked up at the University of Washington back in 1998. It's basically a low-tech dehumidifier. And it turns out the Mars atmosphere is often 100 percent humid.
que muchos cráteres en Marte contienen una capa de hielo. No es un mal lugar para asentar una colonia. Aquí se ve una pequeña excavación hecha por la sonda Phoenix en 2008, que muestra que justo por debajo de la superficie del suelo hay hielo; esa cosa blanca es hielo. En la segunda imagen, tomada unos cuatro días más tarde que la primera, se nota que parte se está evaporando. Los satélites también nos dicen que hay enormes cantidades de agua subterránea en Marte y también glaciares. De hecho, si solo el hielo de los polos marcianos se derritiese la mayor parte del planeta estaría sumergida bajo 9 metros de agua. Así que hay mucha agua allí, pero la mayor parte está congelada y bajo la superficie y se necesita mucha energía y mano de obra para obtenerla. Este es un dispositivo inventado en la Universidad de Washington en 1998. y es básicamente un deshumidificador de baja tecnología. Y resulta que la atmósfera de Marte cuenta a menudo con 100 % de humedad.
So this device can extract all the water that humans will need simply from the atmosphere on Mars. Next we have to worry about what we will breathe. Frankly, I was really shocked to find out that NASA has this problem worked out. This is a scientist at MIT named Michael Hecht. And he's developed this machine, Moxie. I love this thing. It's a reverse fuel cell, essentially, that sucks in the Martian atmosphere and pumps out oxygen. And you have to remember that CO2 -- carbon dioxide, which is 96 percent of Mars' atmosphere -- CO2 is basically 78 percent oxygen. Now, the next big rover that NASA sends to Mars in 2020 is going to have one of these devices aboard, and it will be able to produce enough oxygen to keep one person alive indefinitely. But the secret to this -- and that's just for testing -- the secret to this is that this thing was designed from the get-go to be scalable by a factor of 100. Next, what will we eat? Well, we'll use hydroponics to grow food, but we're not going to be able to grow more than 15 to 20 percent of our food there, at least not until water is running on the surface of Mars and we actually have the probability and the capability of planting crops. In the meantime, most of our food will arrive from Earth, and it will be dried. And then we need some shelter. At first we can use inflatable, pressurized buildings as well as the landers themselves. But this really only works during the daytime. There is too much solar radiation and too much radiation from cosmic rays. So we really have to go underground. Now, it turns out that the soil on Mars, by and large, is perfect for making bricks. And NASA has figured this one out, too. They're going to throw some polymer plastic into the bricks, shove them in a microwave oven,
Así que este dispositivo puede extraer toda el agua que los humanos necesitarán simplemente de la atmósfera marciana. Luego tenemos que preocuparnos por lo que vamos a respirar. Francamente, me sorprendió mucho descubrir que la NASA ha resuelto este problema. Se trata de un científico del MIT llamado Michael Hecht que ha desarrollado esta máquina, Moxie, -- me encanta esta cosa -- es prácticamente una pila de combustible invertida que aspira la atmósfera de Marte y bombea oxígeno. Y hay que recordar que el CO2, -- el dióxido de carbono, que constituye el 96 % de la atmósfera de Marte -- el CO2 es, básicamente un 78 % oxígeno. La próxima gran sonda que la NASA enviará a Marte en 2020 tendrá uno de estos dispositivos a bordo, y podrá producir suficiente oxígeno para mantener a una persona con vida indefinidamente. Pero el secreto de esto, -- y esto es solo una prueba -- es que esta cosa fue diseñada desde el primer momento con un factor de escalabilidad de 100. A continuación, ¿qué comeremos? Bueno, emplearemos la hidroponía para cultivar los alimentos, pero no podremos cultivar más de un 15 a un 20 % de nuestra comida allí, al menos no hasta que haya agua corriente en la superficie marciana y tengamos la oportunidad y la capacidad real de plantar cultivos. Mientras tanto, la mayor parte del alimento llegará desde la Tierra, deshidratada. También necesitamos cobijo. Para empezar, podemos usar edificios hinchables, presurizados, así como los propios módulos de aterrizaje. Pero esto en realidad solo funciona durante el día. Hay demasiada radiación solar y proveniente de los rayos cósmicos, así que realmente tenemos que vivir bajo la superficie. Resulta que el suelo de Marte, por lo general, es perfecto para la fabricación de ladrillos. Y la NASA ha descubierto la manera de hacerlos también. Se añaden polímeros plásticos a los ladrillos, se colocan en un horno de microondas,
and then you will be able to build buildings with really thick walls. Or we may choose to live underground in caves or in lava tubes, of which there are plenty. And finally there's clothing. On Earth we have miles of atmosphere piled up on us, which creates 15 pounds of pressure on our bodies at all times, and we're constantly pushing out against that. On Mars there's hardly any atmospheric pressure. So Dava Newman, a scientist at MIT, has created this sleek space suit. It will keep us together, block radiation and keep us warm. So let's think about this for a minute. Food, shelter, clothing, water, oxygen ... we can do this. We really can. But it's still a little complicated and a little difficult. So that leads to the next big -- really big step -- in living the good life on Mars. And that's terraforming the planet: making it more like Earth, reengineering an entire planet. That sounds like a lot of hubris, but the truth is that the technology to do everything I'm about to tell you already exists. First we've got to warm it up. Mars is incredibly cold because it has a very thin atmosphere. The answer lies here, at the south pole and at the north pole of Mars, both of which are covered with an incredible amount of frozen carbon dioxide -- dry ice. If we heat it up, it sublimes directly into the atmosphere and thickens the atmosphere the same way it does on Earth. And as we know, CO2 is an incredibly potent greenhouse gas. Now, my favorite way of doing this is to erect a very, very large solar sail and focus it -- it essentially serves as a mirror -- and focus it on the south pole of Mars at first. As the planet spins, it will heat up all that dry ice, sublime it, and it will go into the atmosphere. It actually won't take long for the temperature on Mars to start rising, probably less than 20 years. Right now, on a perfect day at the equator, in the middle of summer on Mars, temperatures can actually reach 70 degrees, but then they go down to minus 100 at night. (Laughter) What we're shooting for is a runaway greenhouse effect: enough temperature rise to see a lot of that ice on Mars -- especially the ice in the ground -- melt.
y así se construirán edificios con paredes muy gruesas. O podemos elegir vivir bajo tierra en cuevas o en conductos de lava, porque hay un montón. Y por último, la ropa. En la Tierra tenemos encima kilómetros de atmósfera, lo que ejerce 6,8 kg de presión sobre nuestro cuerpo en cada momento mientras estamos constantemente luchando con ello. Marte apenas tiene presión atmosférica. Dava Newman, científica en el MIT, ha creado este traje espacial elegante. Nos mantendrá a salvo y bloqueará la radiación lo que nos permitirá mantenernos calientes. Así que pensemos en esto por un minuto: Alimento, refugio, ropa, agua, oxígeno. Podemos hacer esto. De verdad podemos. Pero todavía es un poco complicado y un poco difícil. Y esto nos lleva al siguiente paso, -- un paso muy importante -- vivir bien en Marte. y eso significa la terraformación del planeta: de modo que sea similar a la Tierra, re-diseñar todo el planeta. Eso suena muy presuntuoso, pero la verdad es es que la tecnología para hacer lo que digo ya existe. En primer lugar tenemos que calentarlo. Marte es increíblemente frío porque tiene una atmósfera muy tenue. La respuesta está aquí, en los polos marcianos, ya que ambos están cubiertos con una increíble cantidad de dióxido de carbono congelado, o hielo seco. Si lo calentamos, sublimará directamente en la atmósfera y este fenómeno la espesará del mismo modo que ocurre en la Tierra. Como sabemos, el CO2 es un gas de efecto invernadero increíblemente potente. Mi método favorito para hacerlo es construir una vela solar gigante y enfocarla, más o menos como un espejo, empezando por el polo sur marciano. A medida que el planeta gira, todo ese hielo seco, se calentará, sublimará y se liberará en la atmósfera. De hecho, no hará falta mucho tiempo para que aumente la temperatura en Marte; probablemente menos de 20 años. Ahora mismo, un día perfecto en el ecuador, a mediados de un verano marciano la temperatura puede alcanzar los 21° C para luego bajar a - 73 °C por la noche. (Risas) Estamos apostando por un efecto invernadero inmediato: con un suficiente aumento de la temperatura para que gran parte de ese hielo marciano, especialmente el que está bajo la superficie, se derrita. El resto es pura magia.
As the atmosphere gets thicker, everything gets better. We get more protection from radiation, more atmosphere makes us warmer, makes the planet warmer, so we get running water and that makes crops possible. Then more water vapor goes into the air, forming yet another potent greenhouse gas. It will rain and it will snow on Mars. And a thicker atmosphere will create enough pressure so that we can throw away those space suits.
A medida que la atmósfera se espesa, todo mejora. Habrá mayor protección contra las radiaciones, más atmósfera mantendrá al planeta y a nosotros más calientes, por lo que tendremos agua potable, algo que permite el cultivo. Más evaporación en el aire significará otro potente gas invernadero. Lloverá y nevará en Marte. Una atmósfera más densa creará suficiente presión para renunciar a los trajes espaciales.
We only need about five pounds of pressure to survive. Eventually, Mars will be made to feel a lot like British Columbia. We'll still be left with the complicated problem of making the atmosphere breathable, and frankly that could take 1,000 years to accomplish. But humans are amazingly smart and incredibly adaptable. There is no telling what our future technology will be able to accomplish and no telling what we can do with our own bodies. In biology right now, we are on the very verge of being able to control our own genetics, what the genes in our own bodies are doing, and certainly, eventually, our own evolution. We could end up with a species of human being on Earth that is slightly different from the species of human beings on Mars. But what would you do there? How would you live? It's going to be the same as it is on Earth. Somebody's going to start a restaurant, somebody's going to build an iron foundry. Someone will make documentary movies of Mars and sell them on Earth. Some idiot will start a reality TV show. (Laughter) There will be software companies, there will be hotels, there will be bars. This much is certain: it will be the most disruptive event in our lifetimes, and I think it will be the most inspiring. Ask any 10-year-old girl if she wants to go to Mars. Children who are now in elementary school are going to choose to live there. Remember when we landed humans on the Moon? When that happened, people looked at each other and said, "If we can do this, we can do anything." What are they going to think when we actually form a colony on Mars? Most importantly, it will make us a spacefaring species. And that means humans will survive no matter what happens on Earth. We will never be the last of our kind. Thank you. (Applause)
ya que solo hacen falta 2,2 kg de presión para sobrevivir. Finalmente, Marte se parecerá mucho a la Columbia Británica de Canadá. Todavía tendremos que lidiar con el difícil problema de hacer que la atmósfera sea respirable, y francamente eso solo se logrará en 1000 años. Pero los humanos somos unos seres increíblemente inteligentes y adaptables. No hay manera de saber qué logros tecnológicos alcanzaremos y lo que llegaremos a saber que podemos hacer con nuestros propios cuerpos. Hoy en día, estamos a punto de poder controlar nuestra propia genética, lo que están haciendo los genes en nuestro cuerpo, y, desde luego, finalmente controlaremos nuestra propia evolución. Podríamos llegar a tener una especie humana terrestre ligeramente diferente a la especie de humanos marcianos. Pero ¿qué harán allí? ¿Cómo vivirán? Será como en la Tierra. Alguien va a abrir un restaurante, otro una fundición de hierro. Alguien rodará documentales en Marte para venderlos en la Tierra. Algún tonto lanzará un programa de televisión. (Risas) Habrá compañías de software, habrá hoteles, habrá bares. Lo cierto es que será el evento más perturbador de nuestra vida, yo creo que va a ser el más inspirador. Pregunten a cualquier niña de 10 años si quiere ir a Marte. Los niños que ahora están en la escuela primaria optarán por vivir allí. ¿Recuerdan cuando el hombre llegó a la Luna? Cuando eso sucedió, la gente se miraba y decía: "Si podemos hacer esto, podemos hacer cualquier cosa". ¿Qué van a pensar cuando realmente colonicemos Marte? Más importante, seremos una especie de viajeros espaciales. Y eso significa que sobreviviremos sin importar lo que pase en la Tierra. Nunca seremos los últimos de nuestra especie. Gracias. (Aplausos)